<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pronostycacyon [sic] of Erra Pater, Doctor in Astronomye, and phesyke profytable for to kepe the body in helth, [and] Ptholome sayth the same.</title>
            <title>Book of knowledge</title>
            <author>Erra Pater.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 439.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845130</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10015</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17630)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10015)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 49:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pronostycacyon [sic] of Erra Pater, Doctor in Astronomye, and phesyke profytable for to kepe the body in helth, [and] Ptholome sayth the same.</title>
                  <title>Book of knowledge</title>
                  <author>Erra Pater.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me (Robert Wyer) for Richarde Bankes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1545]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erra Pater is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>With title-page woodcuts.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Colophon printed with Wyer's name enclosed in round brackets.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 10518.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 10518 on UMI microfilm reel 49.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10015:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10015:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Pronoſtycacyon of Erra Pater, Doctor in Aſtronomye, and
Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyke, Profytable for to kepe the body in helth, &amp; Ptholome ſayth
the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Ptholomeus.</p>
                  <figDesc>crowned Ptolomy (or Ptolemaeus) and a woman with
astronomical instruments</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prognostication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10015:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I fynde in the ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Aſtronomye / There ben foure
maner of Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in a mannes body of the .iiii. Complexyons. The fyrſte is
blode, the ſeconde blacke Cooler, the thyrde fleumes, &amp; the fourth yelowe
Cooler. And yf one of the .iiii. lacke, all the body ſhuld be anone forthwith
deed, for as moche ſuſteyneth one of theym the body, as the other. And
eueryche of them oughte to be at a certayne, for and one of theym ſermount
the other, all the body ſhall haue domage therby, &amp; all .iiii. be ryght
peryllous, for and the blode ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mount the other, he myghte eſteygner
diſtroye &amp; ouercome the bodye, &amp; make hym to dye, for he gadreth
&amp; congeleth euen ryght on the herte and taketh away the flatte, ſpyrte,
&amp; the brethe, and in that maner (leſteygne) and is ouercome &amp; deade.
But at that tyme whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great courſe taketh hym, he maye ſoone be
aſwaged to leſſe hym a lytel to take away a lytel blod from hym and anone
all wyll aſwage of this peryll.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo the blacke Cooler be right peryllous &amp; they
ſurmounte all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, they maye domage greatly the bodye, &amp; by many
dyuers maners, for they maye cauſe and make the bodye to fall on the euyll
ſyckeneſſe, and leſe his wytte and <pb facs="tcp:10015:2"/>knowledge,
and become a foole, and cauſe alſo the body to be full of euyll ſcabbes,
&amp; often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to be meſell, and maketh a man to be feare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, and a
cowarde, &amp; of many euyll maners. And whan they ſurmounte the other: they
be ryght greuous &amp; domageous. And by herbes, flowres, faſtynge,
abſtynence, drynkes, and medycynes they may be aſwaged.</p>
            <p>¶ The fleumes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be whyte be peryllous when they
ſurmounte the other Coolers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye, they do great domage and hurte, for
they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendre gowtes &amp; many other euyll ſyckeneſſes that be colde,
and they hurte alſo the feete and the handes, and the raynes, and the knees,
the legges, &amp; the tethe, &amp; make the mouthe and the breth ſtynkyng,
&amp; the noſe, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares, &amp; cauſeth many other dyſeaſes and
ſyckeneſſes, but they may be aſwaged by herbes, flowres, rotes,
dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, medycynes, &amp; alſo by vomyſſhynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo the yelowe Coolers, be peryllous, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
ſurmount y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Coolers, in a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes body, they (aſſorbent) the herte
&amp; traueyll the brayne, and maketh all the membres feble and ſofte, and
taketh awaye the wyll and the appetyte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, that he may not eate nor
drynke. And alſo they chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge a manes coloure, and maketh hym to loſe his
ſyght and become blynde, &amp; they may be alſo aſwaged as the other
<pb facs="tcp:10015:3"/>fleumes be, by herbes, flowers,
rootes, and by vomyſſynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Theſe .iiii. humoures be of the .iiii. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions,
and they haue the domynacyon of the body .iiii. tymes in the yeare, and eche of
them a quarter of a yeare.</p>
            <p>¶ The yere is .xii. monthes, that is to ſaye .lii. wekes
and one daye, And this is to vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande .CCC.lx. dayes, &amp; .vi.
houres.</p>
            <div n="winter" type="season">
               <head>¶ The dyſpoſycyon of the fyrſte ſeaſon of
the yere.</head>
               <head type="sub">Capricornus, Aquarius, &amp; Piſces.</head>
               <p>THe fyrſte ſeaſon of the yeare that hathe domynacyon of
the bodye of man, is .iii. Monthes, and they be named theſe thre ſygnes,
Capricorne, Aquario, and Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And theſe thre ſygnes haue power of all
Fleumes of the body of man and woman, and they be colde and moyſte, and they
begyn to reygne the .xxiiii. day of Decembre, &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto the .xxiiii.
day of Marche.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="spring" type="season">
               <head>¶ The dyſpoſycyon of the ſeconde parte of the
yere.</head>
               <head type="sub">Aries, Taurus, and Gemini.</head>
               <p>THe ſeconde parte of the yere, is other .iii. Monthes, and
theſe be the ſygnes, Aries Taurus, and Gemini. And they haue
<pb facs="tcp:10015:3"/>power in the bodye of man of the
blode, &amp; they be hote and moſtye, and they begyn to reygne the .xxiiii.
day of Marche, and dureth vnto the .xxiiii. daye of Iune.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="summer" type="season">
               <head>¶ The dyſpoſycyon of the thyrde ſeaſon of the
yere.</head>
               <head type="sub">Cancer, Leo, and Virgo.</head>
               <p>THe thyrde ſeaſon of the yere, be other .iii. Monthes, and
theſe be the ſygnes, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, Leo, and Virgo, and they haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer within
the body of man of the yelowe Coo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers, and they be hote and dyre, and they
begyn to reygne the .xxiiii. daye of Iune, and dureth vnto the .xxiiii. daye of
Septembre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="autumn" type="season">
               <head>¶ The dyſpoſycyon of the fourthe parte of the
yere.</head>
               <head type="sub">Libra, Scorpio, &amp; Sagittarius.</head>
               <p>THe fourth parte of the yeare, be other .iii. Monthes, and
theſe be the fygnes Libra Scorpio, and Sagittarius, and they be colde and
drye, and they begyn to reygne the .xxiiii. day of Septembre, and dureth vnto
the .xxiiii. daye of Decembre. And by the maner of theſe .iiii. ſeaſons,
euery man may kepe hym from all contraryes of metes and drynkꝭ, and
clothynge, and from other contrarye. And yf a man wyll kepe hym after the maner
that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed <pb facs="tcp:10015:4"/>in this boke, he
ſhalll neuer haue Infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytyes of bodye, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god, Take pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later
of ſpayne and chawe it in thy mouth, for it is good to ſpourge the heed
&amp; the body. Alſo eate fenell ſede, comyn ſede, for eche of theſe
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des dyſtroye the fleumes, that all the euylles in mannes body come
of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="east" type="part">
               <head>¶ Eeſt.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶ Ignis Inuentus et Eſtas.</head>
               <p>¶ The water red and thynne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> groſe male red and
harde, the ſpetyll thycke &amp; clammye. The ſynges Aries, Leo, &amp;
Sagittary, is ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred of coloryke, hote, and drye, and Orientall, &amp; the
ſyckenes be take in theſe ſygnes, it is great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll: but he haue his
medycyne colde &amp; moyſte, and the dyete of the ſame complexcion, then he
may be healed by the grace of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="west" type="part">
               <head>¶ Weſt.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶ Aer Adoleſcentia Ver.</head>
               <p>¶ The water red and thycke, the groſe mater reed and
thynne, the ſpetyll thynne and ſwete, the extremytyues out of courſe, The
ſygnes Gemini, Libra, and Aquarie, is engendred of ſanguyne, hote, and
moyſte, and Occyden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall, the cure is colde and drye, with dyete of the
complexyon, caſcia fiſtula in aqua vite.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="north" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10015:4"/>
               <head>¶ Northe.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶ Terra Senectus Autumpnus.</head>
               <p>¶ The water whyte and theynne, the groſe male blacke
and thycke, the ſpetyll thycke and ſowre, the extremytyues vnneth feled,
The ſygnes Taurus, Virgo, and Capricornus: he is engendred of Malencoly colde
and drye, Septemtyrnall, the cure hote and moyſte with the dyete of the
ſame complexyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="south" type="part">
               <head>¶ Sowthe.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶ Aqua Senium et Hyems.</head>
               <p>¶ The water, whyte and thycke, the groſe mater whyte
and thycke, the ſpetyll thynne and ſwete, the extremytiues feble. The
ſygnes Cancer, Scorpio, and Piſces, he is engendred of fleume colde &amp;
moyſt, Meridionall, the cure hote &amp; dyre of the ſame, purgatio trauit
aqua vite, or in potage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="months" type="part">
               <head>¶ The dyſpoſyon of the .xii. Monthes, vpon blode
lettynge.</head>
               <div n="January" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Ianuary.</head>
                  <p>IN the monthe of Ianuarye, let the no blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte
daye for it is peryllous, ne on the .ii. daye, ne the .v. day, ne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .x. daye,
ne the .xv. day, ne the .xix. day, ne the .xx. day, ne the .xxv. day, but as
often as thou wylt drynke <pb facs="tcp:10015:5"/>good whyte
wyne faſtynge. And alwaye take good hede of the dayes that be aboue wrytten,
for they be peryllous for to be let blode on, but the ſygne be ryght good for
blode lettynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="part">
                  <head>¶ February.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the monthe of February, eate no potage of hokkes
or maloys, for that is venym. And yf thou haue nede to blede, on the wreſt on
the vay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of thy thombe, blede not on the .iii. daye, ne on the .vi. daye, ne
on the .viii. daye. But on the .xiiii. day is ryght good, ne blede not on the.
xvii. daye, ne on the .xxvi. daye, ne on the .xxviii. day, but that the ſygne
be very good and thou mayſte choſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Marche.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the monthe of Marche, eate fygges, rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyns,
&amp; ſwete meates &amp; drynkes and hote mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And let the blode on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ryght arme on the .v. daye, or on the .vii. daye, or on the .xvii. daye, for
that is good agaynſt all maner of Febres, but beware blede not the fyrſte
daye, ne the .xv. daye, ne on the xvi. daye, ne on the .xix. daye, ne on the.
xxviii. daye, &amp; thou maye choſe. And yf thou do loke that the ſygne be
right very good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="April" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Apryll.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the monthe of Apryll, blede on the lefte arme on
the .iii. daye, or on the .xi. daye, or on <pb facs="tcp:10015:5"/>the.
xv. daye, and thou ſhall haue no great hede ache, ne leſe thy ſyght that
yere. And vſe freſſhe and hote meates, but blede not on the .vii. daye,
ne on the .viii. daye, ne on the .x. daye, ne on the .xx. daye, for theſe
dayes be not ryghte good for bledynge.☞<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="May" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Maye.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the moneth of Maye, ryſe erely, &amp; eate and
drynke by tyme, vſe hote metes &amp; drynkes, but eate neyther of hed nor
fote whyle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maye laſte. And let the blode on the fyrſte daye, or on the.
xviii. daye, on whiche arme thou wylt, or on the .xxvii. daye, or on the.
xxviii. daye, &amp; it ſhall moche helpe the agaynſt all maner of euylles.
But beware that thou blede not on the .iii. day, ne the .vi. daye, ne the .xxv.
daye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="June" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Iune.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the moneth of Iune, ſome Phyſycyens ſaye,
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is good euery daye to drynke a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyte of colde water faſtynge. And
rule the of thy mete &amp; thy drynke meſurably, &amp; eate letuſe and
ſawge, and yf thou haue nede to blede, ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de on the .xxviii. daye for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is
ryght good. But beware that thou blede not on the .vii. daye, ne on the .x.
daye, ne on the .xv. daye, ne on the .xvi. daye, ne on the .xxii. daye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10015:6"/>
                  <head>¶ Iuly.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the moneth of Iuly, kepe the from Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherye, for
than thy brayne and thy humoures ben alwaye open. And blede not in this
mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, but yf thou haue great nede. And than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware alwaye that thou blede
not vpon thr .xiii. daye, ne on the .xv. day, ne on the .xix. daye, ne on the
xxii. daye, for it is very daungerous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Auguſt.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the moneth of Auguſt, eate no maner of wortes,
nor of no maner of hote meates nor drynkes of ſpycerye, nor blede not on the
fyrſt day, ne on the .xx. day ne on the .xxix. day, ne on the .xxx. daye. The
other dayes thou mayſt ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for great nede yf the ſygne be good for
blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de lettynge, but not els and thou loue thy ſelfe in good healthe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="September" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Septembre.</head>
                  <p>¶ In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moneth of Septembre, al maner fruy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te that is
rype and not infected is good for to eate. And bled on the .xvii. day, or on
the .xxvii. daye, &amp; of the dropſy, frenſe, and palſye, ne of the
fallynge euyll drede the not of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare. And yf thou haue nede to blede
more. Beware that thou blede not on the .iii. day, ne on the .iiii. daye, ne on
the .xvi. daye, ne on the .xxi. daye, ne on the .xxii. daye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="October" type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10015:6"/>
                  <head>¶ Octobre.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the moneth of Octobre, drynke good &amp; holſome
wyne, and blede not, but that great nede make the, and loke that the ſygne be
very good. But yet beware that thou blede not on the .iii. day, ne on the .vi.
day, ne on the .xvi. day ne on the .xxiiii. daye, &amp; thou wylt do well.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="November" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Nouembre.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the moneth of Nouembre, blede not but for nede,
for all thy blode is gadred that tyme vpon thy heed vayne. Bathe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not but
vent the a lytell of graſynge, for than ben all thyne humours ouer quycke for
to blede, and yf caſe be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haue great nede for to blede, beware of
the .v. day, &amp; the .vi. day, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xv. day, &amp; the .xix daye, and
the .xxviii. daye, and the .xxix. daye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="December" type="part">
                  <head>¶ Decembre.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the monthe of Decembre, blede not but yf thou haue
great nede for the caſe. And blede than on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxvi. daye, for it is ryght
good. And in caſe thou haue more nede for to blede, bewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the .vii.
daye, &amp; the .xv. daye, and of the .xvi. daye, &amp; of the .xvii. daye, and
of the .xxii. daye, and in this monthe come nyghe no fyre with thy
ſhankes.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>¶ Thus endeth theſe .xii. Monthes.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="days" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10015:7"/>
               <head>¶ For to vnderſtande &amp; know the yeres that
ſhall be plentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and in great habun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of goodes.</head>
               <div n="Sunday" type="part">
                  <head>¶ In die dominica, That is Sondaye.</head>
                  <p>IN the yeare that Ianyuere ſhall entre on the Sondaye, the
wynter ſhall be colde and moyſte, and the Sommer ſhal be hote, and the
tyme of Harueſt ſhall be wyndy and rayny with great habundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of corne,
of wynes, and of other graynes, and of all Gardayne fruyte and herbes. There
ſhall be lytell Oyle, habun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhal be of all maner of fleſſhe,
ſome great newes ſhall men here ſpoken, of Kynges, of Prelates of the
churche, and other erthly pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, great warres and robboryes ſhall be made,
and many yonge people ſhall dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Monday" type="part">
                  <head>¶ In die Lune, that is Monday.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the yeare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ianyuere ſhall entre on the
Mondaye, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynter ſhalbe peaſyble ynoughe, and the ſomer ſhall be
very temperate. Than ſhall be great flodes of waters, that ſhall breke out
of theyr lymyttes and bondes, and many <pb facs="tcp:10015:7"/>ſhyppes
vpon the ſee ſhall peryſſhe, &amp; in that yeare ſhall raygne dyuers
ſyckeneſſes, &amp; chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of great lordes ſhal be made, many women
ſhall peryſſhe in trauaylynge with chylde, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great lordes ſhall
dye. That yeare ſhall be lytell graſſe and muſtarde ſede, but there
ſhalbe plentie of corne and wynes, and good chepe of fleſſhe, and but
lytell oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Tuesday" type="part">
                  <head>¶ In die Martis, that is Tueſdaye.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the yeare that Ianyuere ſhall enter on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Tueſdaye, the wynter ſhall be chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable and not ſtedfaſt, for in the
Prymetyme, of trueth it ſhall freeſe, and that ſhall hurte ſore the
Rye, the Vynes, and the flowres, &amp; the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſhall be drye, hote, &amp;
burnynge, in ſo moche that the herbes of the gardynes ſhall haue no power
to come out of the grounde. All thynges ſhall be deare, ſaue onely corne,
many men ſhall dye of the blody flyxe. There ſhall be no tydynges of
thondres, lyghtnynges, &amp; tempeſtes, but all fleſſhe ſhal be deare,
many wynes ſhall tourne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Wednesday" type="part">
                  <head>¶ In dei Marcurij, that is wedneſdaye.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the yeare that Ianyuere ſhall entre on the
wedneſdaye, the wynter ſhall be temperate, but in the ende there ſhall be
ſnowes and froſte. <pb facs="tcp:10015:8"/>The prymetyme
ſhall be raynye, great habun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of all cornes, of wynes, of fruytes, of
haye, of graſſe, and generally of all good thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſhall
be a lytell clowdy, by the whiche therof ſhall come great ſyckeneſſes,
po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re labourers as hande craftes, and artyfycers, ſhall gayne meately well
this yeare. Many the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhal be, by whom the meane people ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore
pylled and diſcomforted, great waters, bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayll, and ſlaughters ſhall be
towardes the myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the yeare, by the whiche ſhall come great goodes to
ſome men. In the ende of the yeare, there ſhall be dyuers peſtylences,
botches, and fallynge euylles, and in eſpecyall next the ſee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Thursday" type="part">
                  <head>¶ In die Iouis, that is Thurſdaye.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the yeare that Ianyuere ſhall entre on the
Thurſdaye, the wynter ſhall be longe and moſte parte drye, and this yeare
ſhal be very hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſome. The prymetyme ſhal be very wyndy, the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer
ſhal be good and temperat, and Harueſt ſhall be moſt parte rayny, by
the whiche the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall ſore breke out of theyr bondes. The wheete
&amp; wynes ſhall be good chepe, there ſhall be of otes, of haye, of
graſſe, and of fruytes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently ynoughe, great warre and dyuyſyon
ſhall be betwene the Churche and the kynges, &amp; <pb facs="tcp:10015:8"/>the
prynces, and in the ende the prynces ſhall haue victoryes of theyr
enterpryſes, women ſhall ſet them ſelfe moche to lechery, the people
ſhall be well eaſed of taxes and talleges.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Friday" type="part">
                  <head>¶ In die Veneris, that is Frydaye.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the yeare that Ianyuere ſhall entre on the
Frydaye, the wynter ſhal be longe and drye And the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer vnholſome,
Harueſt ſhal be dry all corne ſhal be deere, the vyntage ſhal be good
ynough, and habundaunce of oyle, of fruyte, of haye, of graſſe, and of all
gradayne herbes. The worlde ſhal be ſore perſecuted with dyuers
ſyckeneſſes, as of ſore iyes, and of all etyckes, many yonge chyldren
ſhall dye. Great thon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres, lyghtnynges, and tempeſtes ſhall be, that
ſhall greue ſore all the grounde. There ſhall be earth quakes, and good
chepe clothe poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhal gayne lytell or no thyng, many beeſtes
ſhall dye for hunger, for the dyuerſyte and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladye of the tyme.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Saturday" type="part">
                  <head>¶ In die Sabbati, that is Saterdaye.</head>
                  <p>¶ In the yeare that Ianyuere ſhall enter on the
Saterdaye, the wynter ſhall be temperate ſuffycyentlye. And in the
Prymetyme ſhall be froſtes, the whiche ſhall dyſtroye the Ryes, the
<pb facs="tcp:10015:9"/>vynes, the oyles, and the fruytes.
The ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer ſhall be meately temperate, the Harueſt tyme ſhall be drye,
the otes &amp; other corne ſhal be good chepe, all gardayne herbes ſhall be
good chepe, ynoughe, and fleſſhe ſhal be good chepe, many olde people
ſhall dye, feuers tercyans ſhall gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſore the worlde, that ſhall be
ſycke throughe euyll heete. And many murmuracyons, warre and murthers ſhall
be done, by the one agaynſt the other, &amp; neyghboures agaynſt
neyghboures and many other caſes ſhall be often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted and done.
☞<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Finis. ¶ Thus endeth the Pronoſtycacyon
☞for euer.☜</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted by me (Robert Wyer) For Richarde Bankes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="privilege">
            <p>Cum priuilegio, Ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10015:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
